"The Best Daily Dose of Taurine"
The remarkable trial showing
that taurine supplementation
improved the lifespan
and healthspan of animals
used doses
that may far exceed
the recommended safe
consumption limits in humans.
At the press conference,
the corresponding author said
that they would not recommend
people to start taking
taurine supplements
to try to preserve health
or slow aging.
Not only do we have
no human studies
showing that kind of benefit,
we don’t even know
what the potential risks are,
since we don’t have large,
long-term human safety trials.
In my last video,
I talked about those
who might be particularly
sensitive to taurine,
and what happens,
at least in the short term,
if we exceed
recommended intakes.
If,
after careful consideration,
you still want to give it a try,
what source, dose,
and frequency might be best?
In terms of frequency,
the bump in our blood stream
only lasts about six hours.
So, we’d presumably
want to split doses
to maintain higher levels;
for example,
three times a day,
like, at every meal.
What dose?
Well, just for context,
most people get
between 40 and 400 milligrams
a day through their diet.
So, that’s like,
a normal, typical daily dose.
If our goal is
to restore youthful levels,
we’d want to bump our levels up
from around
the 50-micromole range
to maybe the 100 or 200 range.
Here’s a study
where participants
got 400 milligrams a day,
up at the higher end
of a normal dietary dose,
for a week, and got levels
into that upper range.
Here, a two-gram daily dose
also pushed levels
into that target range,
but, unfortunately, studies
are all over the place.
Here’s a good illustration
of why using
a blood target level
doesn’t work.
These 10 people were given
one gram of taurine
three times a day for a month.
First of all,
see how they started
all over the place,
from 18 to more than 600?
And after a month,
most of their levels went up,
but sometimes
they actually went down.
And this measured levels
in the plasma or serum,
the liquid
part of the blood.
Levels in
the blood cells themselves
can be hundreds of times higher,
and levels in whole blood
don’t seem to correlate
with levels in plasma.
So, should we measure taurine
in whole blood?
But whole blood levels
don’t move as much
or even
in any significant amount
in response to supplementation.
In this study,
researchers gave people
1.66 grams twice a day,
shooting up plasma levels
to a thousand,
yet, at the end of the week,
there was no change
in levels in the muscle,
based on muscle biopsies.
The body didn’t seem to care
what was happening in the blood
it kept
the tissue levels stable.
In contrast, when rats
are given taurine,
the levels of taurine
in their muscles go up.
So, maybe taurine is like
the NAD-booster debacle?
You can rewatch my webinar
for a recap,
but, remember how NAD
also declined with age?
And restoration
of youthful levels
with supplements
caused all these
amazing benefits in lab animals,
so, a gazillion-dollar
NAD supplement industry
was born?
But, when finally
put to the test in people,
they totally flopped.
And, no wonder.
In rodents,
these supplements
actually boosted NAD levels
in their tissues,
but we’re not rodents,
and the supplements all failed
to raise levels in our muscles.
So, maybe when we have
human trials on taurine,
they’ll also fail
in the same way.
But maybe not.
For those
who don’t want to wait,
what dose should we shoot for?
We really have no idea,
but from all the human trials
that have been done,
the most commonly used dose
in the blood pressure
lowering trials,
which is probably the best
demonstrated benefit
that also best lowers
oxidative stress
and inflammation
is about 1.5 grams a day.
So, that would be 500 milligrams
three times a day.
Okay, that’s the dose
and the frequency,
but what’s the best source?
That’s what I’ll cover, next.